We’ve all been there.
我们都有过这样的经历。
One minute you’re searching for something serious, like a recipe for dinner, or something for work, and the next you’ve been sucked in by endless videos of cats doing funny things after seeing a catchy title in your suggested videos column.
前一秒你还在搜索正经内容，比如晚餐食谱或是工作相关资料，下一秒就被推荐视频栏里的吸睛标题吸引，深陷于没完没了的猫咪搞笑视频中。
They’re compelling, engrossing and captivating, and you can end up spending hours watching kittens make funny noises or mistiming jumps.
这些视频极具吸引力，让人沉浸其中、无法自拔，你甚至会花上好几个小时，看小猫们发出滑稽的叫声，或是在跳跃时判断失误出糗。
But why do these videos so often end up going viral?
但为什么这类视频总能轻易走红？
What makes them so enthralling?
是什么让它们如此令人着迷？
And why are they more popular than dog videos?
又为什么它们比狗狗视频更受欢迎呢？
First, let’s talk about stereotypes.
首先来聊聊刻板印象。
When many of us think about dogs, we imagine them rolling over onto their backs, tongues hanging out, or making a mess.
在很多人眼里，狗狗就是那种会四脚朝天打滚、吐着舌头喘气，或是把东西弄得一团糟的形象。
They seem trusting and innocent – and they do silly things.
它们看起来轻信人类又天真可爱，经常会做些傻事。
Cats, on the other hand, seem somewhat more refined and independent. There’s a reason we have an expression ‘cool cat’.
而猫咪则显得更优雅、更独立，难怪英语里会有“酷猫”这样的说法。
In short, cats seem more serious – and savvy.
简而言之，猫咪给人的感觉更严肃，也更精明。
If we can get one over on a cat and make them do something like get in a box that slides down a hill, it’s comical.
要是能捉弄一下猫咪，比如让它们钻进会从山坡上滑下去的箱子里，画面就会十分滑稽。
But with a dog, it’s not as funny because they trust you – and it’s easier.
但换成狗狗的话，就没那么好笑了，因为狗狗容易信任人，捉弄它们也更容易。
Tricking a cat, due to their wiliness, has more payoff.
正因为猫咪生性狡黠，能骗到它们才更有成就感。
The internet is filled with videos of cats making funny faces or reacting strangely.
网上到处都是猫咪做鬼脸或做出怪异反应的视频。
But why are they so funny?
但它们为什么这么好笑呢？
Well, simply – it’s unexpected.
原因很简单——因为这些画面完全出人意料。
If you saw a cat walking down the street coolly or observing and preparing to attack a mouse, it wouldn’t be funny.
如果看到一只猫咪在街上酷酷地走着，或是观察老鼠准备攻击，你肯定不会觉得好笑。
But if that cat was walking sideways, wearing a silly costume, or becoming best friends with the mouse, suddenly we might start to laugh.
可要是这只猫走起了螃蟹步，穿着傻傻的衣服，甚至和老鼠成了好朋友，你肯定会忍不住笑出声。
Watching a cat that is normally majestic walk clunkily or pull a bizarre face is hilarious because it’s not something we would normally associate with that animal.
看到一只平时姿态优雅的猫咪走起路来笨手笨脚，或是挤出让人忍俊不禁的怪表情，会觉得格外滑稽，因为这些行为和我们对猫咪的固有印象完全不符。
It’s like watching someone who is normally very serious get the giggles. In some ways, we’re all laughing at their fall from grace.
这就像看到一个平时不苟言笑的人突然哈哈大笑一样，某种程度上，我们就是在笑它们“形象崩塌”的样子。
So the next time you see one of those many memes of cats in awkward situations or videos that make you chuckle, try to remember why it’s so funny.
所以下次当你刷到那些猫咪出糗的表情包，或是让你会心一笑的猫咪视频时，不妨想想它们好笑的原因。
And spare a thought for all those dogs that are trying to entertain us too.
也别忘了，还有那么多狗狗也在努力逗我们开心呢。